Guide to the Oral History of the American Left Collection OH.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Oral History of the American Left Main Series, 1940-2011
  - Pauline Dougherty, Jan, 1982; cuid1257 (Box 15, Cd Dougherty 1-4, Box 2, Cassette 70 A-D)
    Dougherty discusses her background in a shoe-producing town, college politics during the Depression, white collar union activity, the McCarthy Era, and reflections.
    Interview by Sy Singer.
    Duration: 224 minutes
  - Susan Drake-Raphals, May 7, 1983; cuid1258 (Box 15, Cd Drake-Raphals 1, Box 2, Cassette 71)
    Drake-Raphals discusses her role in the Workers Party and C.L.R. James in the 1940s.
  - Hal Draper, Nov 5, 1983; cuid1259 (Box 7, Folder 25, Box 15, Cassette Draper 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 72 B, Box 2, Cassette 72 A)
    Draper characterizes the interview as "a rundown on the birth of neo-Shactmanism," and it includes an analysis of Shactman's personality and the trajectory of the Shactman group's activities. As a part of this, Draper discusses the New International, discusses the paper's of board and editorship, his role as editor of Labor Action between 1949-1958, and the tabloid-like nature of that publication. He also discusses the merger of Independent Socialist League and Socialist Party and debates within the Workers Party about Zionism from 1948-1949. Draper also discusses the political disintegration of the Shactmanite group and his move to Berkeley.
    Duration: 128 minutes
  - Walter Duda, Mar 15, 1983; cuid1260 (Box 3, Cassette 73, Box 15, Cd Duda 1)
    Duda discusses the Lithuanian-American Left's activities around Connecticut's Brass Valley during the 1920s-1950s.
    Duration: 24 minutes
  - Jane Dudley, 1981; cuid1261 (Box 7, Folder 26, Box 3, Cassette 74, Box 15, Cd Dudley 1)
    Dudley discusses the relationship between dance and left politics, the New Dance group, Martha Graham, and civil rights.
    Preservation Note: Incubation was attempted on this audiocassette, however it could not be digitized due to its condition.
  - Raya Dunayevskaya, Mar 24, 1983; cuid1262 (Box 3, Cassette 75, Box 15, Cd Dunayevskaya 1-2)
    Dunayevskaya discusses Leon Trotsky and Trotskyism during the 1930s, the Johnson-Forest group during the 1940s, the coal strikes of 1949-1950, and the origins of the Marxist-Humanist organization News and Letters.
  - George Edwards, Nov 4, 1983; cuid1263 (Box 3, Cassette 76 A-C, Box 7, Folder 27, Box 15, Cd G. Edwards 1-3)
    Edwards discusses his political origins as Garveyite during the 1920s, his social life in the 1920s-1930s, his experience as semiprofessional football player, his work as a prohibition-era gangster and factory worker, his activities as a Communist organizer in the Kansas-Nebraska district during the 1930s-1940s, and his disillusionment with the Communist movement in Oakland, California during the 1940s-1950s. Edwards also discusses life in Ghana during the 1950s-1960s.
    Duration: 155 minutes in three parts; Preservation note: Tape incubated for binder hydrolysis
  - Herb Edwards, Feb 12, 1972; cuid1264 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    Edwards discusses life in Wisconsin lumber during the early 1900s, the Industrial Workers of the World, Elmer Smith, the repression of the IWW, Edwards' time at San Quentin, and the ebb of the IWW.
    Interview by Tom Copeland & Tracy Dalton.
  - Hodee Edwards, Nov 12, 1983; cuid1265 (Box 15, Cd H. Edwards 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 78 A-B)
    Edwards discusses her background in Boston Jewish community during the 1920s-30s, her experience as a Communist activist in California during the 1940s, her activities crusading for women's rights, the publication People's World in 1949, her life in Ghana during the 1950s-60s, and life events from the 1960s-1980s.
    Duration: 126 minutes in two parts
  - Peter Elish, Jun 27, 1983; cuid1266 (Box 15, Cd Elish 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 77)
    Interview addresses the activities of the Slovenian-American mutual aid society SNPJ (Slovenska Narodna Podporna Jednota) and the relationship between Slavic ethnic identities and the left.
    Duration: 95 minutes
  - Melech Epstein, Jan 9, 1974; cuid1267 (Box 15, Cd M. Epstein 1, Box 3, Cassette 79)
    Interview includes recollections of Epstein's experiences since his immigration from Warsaw in 1913, including editorship of Morgen Freiheit. He also provides comments on Yiddish publications and Jewish life in America, the Cold War, Israel, and 1970s American politics.
    Duration: 61 minutes
  - Virginia Epstein, Mar 30, 1981; cuid1268 (Box 3, Cassette 80 A-B, Box 7, Folder 29, Box 15, Cd V. Epstein 1-2)
    The interview covers Epstein's background in Dallas, Texas (born 1885) as child of mixed Episcopalian-Jewish marriage. It also covers her time in New York from 1908, Socialist Party activities during the 1910s, Communist Party involvement from the 1920s, the American Council on US-Soviet Friendship, the Committee of American Women, and local political activities in Queens, New York.
  - Ernest Erber, Apr 23, 1984; cuid1269 (Box 81, Cassette 365 A-B, Box 15, Cd Erber 1-2)
  - Seymour Faber, Mar 30, 1983; cuid1271 (Box 15, Cd Faber 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 82 A-B, Box 7, Folder 30)
    Interview includes discussion of radical Zionism, the Johnson-Forest Tendency, and activities in Detroit during the 1930s-1960s.
    Duration: 86 minutes
  - Elmer Felhaber, Feb 5, 1981; cuid1272 (Box 15, Cd Felhaber 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 83 A-B)
    General note
    Index available
    Felhaber discusses Minnesota newspaper unionism during the 1930s, the CIO and the Communist Party, the Ohio Left after World War II, and his travels abroad.
    Duration: 4 minutes; Preservation Note: One of the audiocassettes could not be digitized due to its condition.
  - Duncan Ferguson (Memorial Meeting), 1975; cuid1273 (Box 3, Cassette 84, Box 15, Cd Ferguson 1)
    Eulogy by Harry Ring for Duncan Ferguson, a sculptor and activist in Socialist Workers Party during the 1940s-1970s.
  - Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Dec 1981; cuid1274 (Box 3, Cassette 85, Box 9, Folder 10, Box 15, Cd Ferlinghetti 1-2)
    Interview includes an analysis of the Beat Generation in retrospect and the relationship between the San Francisco avant-garde arts scene and anarchism during the 1940s through the early 1950s. Ferlinghetti also discusses the formation of the City Lights book store and publishing company, and artists in 1980s.
  - Joseph Figueredo, Nov 3, 1983; cuid1275 (Box 15, Cd Figuerdo 1-4, Box 3, Cassette 86 A-D, Box 7, Folder 31)
    Figueredo discusses the Portuguese-American Left in New Bedford and Fall River, Massachusetts during the 1930s-1940s. He speaks the beginning of his introduction to politics during the strikes of the 1920s and Communist role. He addresses the lack of formal fraternal and cultural structure and absence of regular Portuguese-language Communist press. Additionally, the interview covers the use of local radio, Cold War pressures during the 1940s, his departure to San Francisco, and activities in International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU) from the 1950s-1980s.
    Duration: 242 minutes in four parts
  - Bruno Fischer, Nov 1982; cuid1276 (Box 80, Cassette 308 C, Box 15, Cd Fischer 1)
  - Morris Fisher, Mar 16, 1983; cuid1277 (Box 16, Cd Fisher 1, Box 3, Cassette 87)
    Fisher discusses left politics and Jewish culture from the 1930s-1970s. Topics include labor Zionism and the Workmen's Circle, the Jewish Socialist Farband, and the Miami Beach Yiddishkayt.
  - Jacob Fisherman, Nov 3, 1979; cuid1278 (Box 10, Cassette 393, Box 16, Cd Fisherman 1)
  - Henry Foner, Mar 29, 1976; cuid1279 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    Foner discusses being driven out of teaching during the late 1940s, industrial and union activities during the 1948-1970s, the Communist Party, and Ben Gold.
    Interview by Russell Karr.
  - Edith Fox, July 1981; cuid1280 (Box 10, Cassette 419 A-B, Box 16, Cd Fox 1-4)
    Interview by Nora Wainer.
    Historical/Biographical Note
    Edith Fox was born in the Soviet Union, and her family immigrated to Philadelphia when she was a child. She became a socialist through her involvement in Hashomer as a child. As an adult, she joined the Worker's Party, then became followers of C.L.R. James (Johnson-Forest Tendency), and joined the Socialist Workers Party. Fox and her husband Art moved to Detroit and became active in the with the democratization faction of the United Auto Workers Union. The Foxes worked on a Ford assembly line for twenty years. They stayed in the SWP until the 1960s.
    The interview was taken by Nora Wainer in Los Angeles in 1981 for an oral history project on radical women with a focus on Trotskyist Women.
  - Emmanuel Fried, 1977-1983; cuid1281 (Box 80, Cassette 310 A-E, Box 16, Cd Fried 1-6)
    Several recordings of readings and interviews of Emmanuel Fried. The first disk contains a May 1983 discussion for Buffalo radio station WBNY with topics including education, acting, union organizing, writing, impact of blacklist on career. The second and third disks are the recording of a Niagara-Erie writing conference held at St. John's Grace Episcopal Church in Buffalo, New York on Oct 30, 1980. Fried gives a reading from his plays and there is also a reading by author Peter Mathiessen. The fourth disk contains a radio interview of Fried by John Nash for WADU in Buffalo, taken in Mar 1980. The fifth disk contains a readings from the Labor Writers Workshop on Jun 8, 1977, introduced by Emmanuel Fried and broadcast on WBFO of Buffalo. The sixth disk contains the recording of a New Letters on the Air (Kansas City, Missouri) broadcast of readings and an interview of Fried from Jun 1978.
  - William (Bill) Friedland, May 6, 1983; cuid1282 (Box 3, Cassette 89, Box 16, Cd Friedland 1)
    Friedland discusses the cultural perspective of the Workers Party, role of music in Friedland's life and creation of the record Songs for Sectarians, college teaching, and sympathy for antiwar students during the 1960s.
    Duration: 47 minutes
  - Isadore Friedman & Max Fishgold, Mar 15, 1983; cuid1283 (Box 16, Cd Friedland & Fishgold 1, Box 3, Cassette 90)
    Interview addresses union activities and the Left from the 1930s-1950s.
  - Mary Gale, Jan 29, 1982; cuid1284 (Box 3, Cassette 91 A-C, Box 16, Cd Gale 1-3)
    Gale discusses growing up in East New York and Queens in the 1910s-1920s, International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) during the 1920s-1930s, the Scottsboro case, and the American Labor Party. She also discusses family and home life in relation to her work and political activism.
    Duration: 115 minutes in three parts
  - Sam Garber, Nov 5, 1979; cuid1285 (Box 10, Cassette 395, Box 16, Cd Garber 1)
  - Alex and Faye Gardner, Abe Kantor, and Hyman Hodes, Mar 15, 1983; cuid1286 (Box 3, Cassette 93 A-B, Box 16, Cd Gardners, Kantor & Hodes 1-2)
    Topics covered in the interview include Jewish and Italian radicalism during the 1930s-1950s, the Unemployed Councils, the Workers' Club, Works Progress Administration, the Garibaldi Clubs, work as Vito Marcantonio's campaign manager, and union activities.
  - Sender Garlin, Oct 14, 1976; cuid1287 (Box 16, Cd Garlin 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 92 A-B)
    Interview includes discussion of Garlin's background in the Socialist Party in the 1910s and his time at the Daily Worker in the 1920s-1930s, including the paper's atmosphere and humor.
    Duration: 122 minutes in two parts
  - Hugo Gellert, Apr 4, 1984; cuid1288 (Box 3, Cassette 94 A-B, Box 16, Cd Gellert 1-2, Box 7, Folder 33)
    Interview includes discussion of immigration from Hungary to the United States and return to Hungary during World War I. It also covers Gellert's work as an artist and cartoonist for commercial publications The New Yorker and New York, the Hungarian-American Left newspaper Uj Elore, and radical arts and literary journal The Masses. Interview includes Gellert's recollections of fellow Masses contributor John Reed.
  - Sophie Melvin-Gerson, Mar 13, 1976; cuid1289 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    Interview includes description of background and youth in Ukraine, Massachusetts, and New York. It also includes discussion of Gerson's involvement in the Young Communist League and the events of the Passaic and Gastonia textile strikes.
    Interview by Alan Safron.
  - Joseph Giganti, Jul 26, 1983; cuid1290 (Box 7, Folder 35, Box 16, Cd Giganti 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 96 A-B)
    Interview includes discussion of the Italian-American Communist newspaper II Lavoratore and its editorial staff and theatrical commentary. Giganti also discusses the nature of Italian-American Left in Chicago during the 1920s through 1940s, "anti-Red" police squad in Chicago, Giganti's expulsion from Communist movement, early Trotskyism, leftist activities of different ethnic groups in Chicago during the 1930s. Other subjects commented upon are the barber's union and Giganti's thoughts on the activities of various factions including those following Oehler, Lovestone, Cannon, and Muste.
    Duration: 89 minutes in two parts
  - Katya Gilden, Nov 21, 1976; cuid1291 (Box 16, Cd Gilden 1-2, Cassette 309A, Box 3, Cassette 95 A-B)
  - Todd Gitlin, Mar 1, 1970; cuid1292 (Box 16, Cd Gitlin 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 97)
    Interview documents the activities of Students for a Democratic Society during the 1960s.
  - Barbara Gittings, Jul 26, 1983; cuid1293 (Box 3, Cassette 98 A-C, Box 16, Cd Gittings 1-4)
    Interview discusses the gay liberation movement during the 1950s-1970s.
    Interview by Howard August.
  - Jessie Glaberman, Aug 17, 1977 - Sep 3, 1977; cuid1294 (Box 7, Folder 36/37, Box 16, Cd J. Glaberman 1-10, Box 3, Cassette 99 A-G)
    Interview covers the Socialist Workers Party and Workers Party in New York, Philadelphia and Detroit during the 1930s-1950s.
    Interviews by Lyn Goldfarb and Ruth Meyerowitz.
  - Martin Glaberman, Mar 29, 1983; cuid1295 (Box 3, Cassette 100, Box 16, Cd M. Glaberman 1)
    Glaberman discusses the Johnson-Forest Tendency in New York and Detroit during the 1940s-1950s.
  - Ruth Glassman, Feb 1, 1979; cuid1296 (Box 16, Cd Glassman 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 101 A-B)
    Glassman discusses the American Youth Congress during the 1930s, World War II and shop agitation, women in factories, and the United Electrical Workers.
    Duration: 78 duration in two parts
  - Albert Glotzer, Oct 31, 1934; cuid1297 (Box 17, Cd Glotzer 1-3, Box 3, Cassette 335 A-B)
  - Albert Glotzer, Dec 21, 1983; cuid1298 (Box 17, Cd Glotzer 4-7, Box 7, Folder 38, Box 3, Cassette 102 A-C)
    Interview covers Glotzer's family background in Russia and Chicago, the Communist Party during the 1920s, American Trotskyism during the late 1920s-30s, and the Workers Party during the 1940s. The last cassette contains a narration by Glotzer in response to written questions by Jon Bloom.
    Duration: 193 minutes in four parts
  - Lillian Gold, Apr 4, 1982; cuid1299 (Box 3, Cassette 103, Box 7, Folder 39, Box 17, Cd Gold 1-2)
    Interview covers Gold's youth in New York City, her recollections of World War I, seeking employment, her involvement in the Socialist Party in 1933, her activities with the War Resisters' League, Franklin Delano Roosevelt and the trade union movement, and union work with teachers in 1950.
  - Itche Goldberg, Jun 5, 1982; cuid1300 (Box 7, Folder 40, Box 17, Cd Goldberg 1, Box 4, Cassette 104)
    Interview covers Goldberg's role as editor of Yiddishe Kultur, his early literary influences, an analysis of the development of Yiddish literature, political and introspective approaches to literature, and literary criticism. Goldberg also discusses the future of the Yiddish language and literature.
  - Itche Goldberg, Feb 16, 1983; cuid1301 (Box 17, Cd Goldberg 2, Box 4, Cassette 105)
    Interview contains Goldberg's reflections on secular and religious aspects of Jewish cultural identity and an examination of unique characteristics of Jewish humor.
  - Goldens Bridge Colony, 1984; cuid1302 (Box 17, Box 10, Cassette 425)
    This recording documents life and political outlooks of the residents in this Westchester County cooperative community from its founding in 1927 through the 1950s.
  - Mollie Goldstein, Nov 7, 1981; cuid1303 (Box 7, Folder 41, Box 17, Cd M. Goldstein 1-2, Box 4, Cassette 106 A-B)
    Interview topics include the Communist Party, women's organizations, price and rent protests in Brooklyn and the Bronx, and activism during the 1930s.
  - Nina Goldstein, Mar 19, 1980; cuid1304 (Box 7, Folder 42, Box 4, Cassette 107 A-D, Box 17, Cd N. Goldstein 1-4)
    Interview documents Goldstein's early life in Russia and Canada, her work and political life in Brownsville and East Flatbush, Brooklyn during the 1920s-1930s, and the activities of the Communist Party. The interview also covers the Morgen Freiheit, the International Workers Order, Russian War Relief and aid to Israel during the 1940s, and the Jewish cultural movement in Miami Beach.
  - Walter Goldwater, Feb 15, 1983; cuid1305 (Box 17, Cd Goldwater 1-2, Box 4, Cassette 108 A-B)
    Goldwater discusses C.L.R. James during the 1920s-1960s, the Workers Party during the 1940s, Trotskyism, anti-Stalinism, neo-conservatism, Pan-Africanism, and Eric Williams.
  - Helen Goodman, Oct 20, 2002; cuid1306 (Box 2, Cassette 108A, Box 7, Folder 43, Box 17, Cd Goodman 1-2)
    Interview includes discussions of childhood in Brooklyn and early jobs, the Great Depression, and work in defense plants during World War II. Activity in the UE Local 1707, American Labor Party, and Jewish Association Services for the Aged are discussed, as are May Day parades and her father's socialist activities. The interview also includes comments on the Paul Robeson concert at Peekskill and Rosenberg executions. Goodman also talks about members of her family and working with the Jewish Association Services for the Aged.
    Interview by Laura Helton.
  - Michael Gordon, Mar 25, 1977; cuid1307 (Box 4, Cassette 109, Box 17, Cd Gordon 1)
    Gordon describes his association with Frontier Films, and coming to film through a background with the Film and Photo League and Group Theatre during the 1930s. Gordon discusses and contrasts the politics of Frontier Films and Group Theatre. Interview also includes discussion of Gordon's work on various projects and associates in Hollywood and New York City.
  - Grandma was an Activist, 1983; cuid1308 (Box 4, Cassette 110 A-C, Box 17, Cd Grandma was an Activist 1-3)
    Ruth F. Prago, a member of the Oral History of the American Left staff, developed the idea for a radio series based on interviews to be conducted for the OHAL collection. Together with Pacifica Radio, OHAL received a one-year grant from the New York Council for the Humanities to conduct interviews with twenty-five women about radicalism during the 1930s. Radio producers Beth Friend and Charles Potter used these interviews to make a six-part radio series titled "Grandma Was an Activist," first broadcast in 1983. One of the series interviewers, Bea Lemisch, and three of the women interviewed for the series, participated in a panel discussion at the 1984 Berkshire Conference on Women's History.
    The six half-hour segements of "Grandma was an Activist" include excerpts from OHAL interviews with Louise Thompson, Jane Dudley, Alice Dodge Wolfson, Meridel LeSueur, among others.
    1) The Black and the Red 2) How Do You Spell Relief? 3) On the Line 4) They Shall Not Pass 5) Readin' and Ritin' on the Road to Power 6) Militant Muse
  - Leah Dillon Grant, Jul 24, 1983; cuid1309 (Box 17, Cd Grant 1, Box 4, Cassette 111)
    Interview documents Yiddish literary milieu in 1920s and role of interviewee's uncle, A.M. Dillon. Also covered are the Johnson-Forest Tendency, its leaders and activities during the 1940s, and cultural perspectives.
  - Janet Green, May 29, 2009; cuid1310 (Box 17, Cd Green 1, Box 10)
    Interview regarding Green's experiences growing up in the Bronx and working in New York City.
    Interview by Jeff Eichler.
  - Samuel Greenberg, Oct 27, 1982; cuid1311 (Box 17, Cd Greenberg 1-2, Box 4, Cassette 112 A-B)
    Interview documents the activities of the Yiddish Left in Los Angeles and nationally from the 1930s-1980s. This includes Greenberg's analysis of various personalities in Yiddish literature including Leivick, Avrom Reyzen, Moshe Nadir, and others. He comments on the relative literary merits of the Morgen Freiheit, Forward, and Freie Arbeiter Stimme, and describes the break between the Freiheit and many writers on the Yiddish literary scene.
    Greenberg expresses pessimism regarding Yiddish culture and working class political movements in the 1980s, and details his own loss of faith in the Soviet Union during the preceding decades. Facets of this discussion include the diminished state of Yiddish culture in the Soviet Union, contrasts between his travels there during 1930s and 1980s, and Greenberg's analyses of the reasons for the decline of Jewish progressive movement.
    Duration: 80 minutes in two parts
  - Guardian Forum, May 26, 1973; cuid1312 (Box 4, Cassette 113 A-B, Box 17, Cd Guardian Forum 1-4)
    "What Road to Building a New Communist Party?"; criticism of 1960s politics; history of class struggle.
    Topics included: women's role in class struggle, role of race and nationality in class struggle, discussion of how new Communist Party would be organized, the tension between unity and sects, the activities of the October League
    Hosted by the Guardian newspaper
  - Sarah Gudelman, Nov 3, 1979; cuid1313 (Box 17, Cd Gudelman 1-3, Box 10, Box 396 A-C)
    Interview includes discussion of Sarah Gudelman's youth in Russia and Germany, her family history, immigration to Lower East Side in New York City and work in the garment trade. Other topics include life with her husband, the sculptor Gudelman, and the death of their first child. Also discussed are Sarah Gudelman's work as administrator for 18 progressive shuls in Bronx, her assessments of artists and Yiddish literary figures including Moshe Nadir and Itche Goldberg, and her involvement in the Communist Party.
  - Oive Halonen, Feb 27, 1978; cuid1314 (Box 17, Cd Halonen 1-2, Box 7, Folder 44, Box 4, Cassette 114)
    Halonen discusses Finnish-American radicalism in Minnesota and Oregon during the 1910s-1930s, participation in Spanish Civil War as member of Abraham Lincoln Brigade, and experiences as Seattle machinist during the 1940s-1960s.
  - Michael Hanusiak, Mar 30, 1983; cuid1315 (Box 17, Cd Hanusiak 1, Box 4, Cassette 115)
    Topics covered by this interview include the Ukrainian-American Left, the International Workers Order during the 1930s-1940s, the effects of McCarthyism, problems of organization, publications, and the generational continuity in the ethnic progressive movement through the 1980s.
  - Louis Harap, Mar 19, 1978; cuid1316 (Box 17, Cd Harap 1-4, Box 7, Folder 45, Box 4, Cassette 116 A-B)
    Harap discusses Harvard University during the 1930s, Jewish Survey during the 1940s, Jewish Life during the 1940s-1950s, the Rosenberg case, and Jewish Currents during the 1950s-1970s.
  - Harlem Riots Inquiry, Apr 14, 1965; cuid1317 (Box 6, Reel 386, Box 17, Cd Harlem Riots Inquiry 1)
    Interview with Sanford Katz, the attorney representing defendants from the Progressive Labor Movement who were charged with involvement in the Harlem Riots of 1964. Subjects include criticism of actions of grand jury, selection of the grand jury, and the implications of holding Eleanor Goldstein in contempt multiple times over the same questions.
  - Michael Harrington, Oct 6, 1969; cuid1318 (Box 4, Cassette 117, Box 17, Cd Harrington 1-2)
    Interview covers the "prehistory" of Students for a Democratic Society during the late 1950s and the activities of SDS during the 1960s.
    Duration: 109 minutes
  - Michael Harrington, May 2, 1988; cuid1319 (Box 4, Cassette 117.5 A-C, Box 17, Cd Harrington 3-5)